Preliminary Inventory to the Theodore Draper Papers, 1912-1966
Hoover Institution Archives
Theodore Draper Papers,
1912-1966
67001
Draper, Theodore, 1912-
37 manuscript boxes, 1 phonotape reel (15.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, newspaper issues, and congressional hearings, relating to the revolution led by Fidel Castro in Cuba, political, social, and economic conditions in Cuba, the 1965 crisis and American intervention in the Dominican Republic, and the Communist Party of the United States.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Castro, Fidel, 1927-; Communist Party of the United States of America; Communism; Communism--United States; Cuba; Cuba--History--1959-; Dominican Republic; Dominican Republic--Foreign relations--United States; Dominican Republic--History--Revolution, 1965; United States--Politics and government; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Foreign relations--Dominican Republic; Phonotapes
Container List
- Cuba. Inventory of the collection of material on Fidel Castro's struggle for power in Cuba and the political, economic and social changes following his take-over, 1948-1966
  - Agriculture (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Aguilar Leòn, Luis (Folder 2)
  - Anti-Castro posters (Folder 3)
  - April 1958 strike (Folder 4)
  - April 1961 invasion (Folder 5)
  - Barquín, Ramòn (Folder 6)
  - Batista, Fulgencio (Folder 7)
  - Bettelheim and Dumont (Folder 8)
  - Bogotazo (Folder 8a)
  - Bohemia (Folder 9)
    - 1954 October-1955 July
    - 1956 January-1956 July (Box 2., Folder 10)
    - 1956 July-1957 July (Folder 11)
    - 1957 July-1958 March (Folder 12)
    - 1964 November (Folder 13)
  - Bohemia Libre (Folder 14)
  - British articles on Cuba (Folder 15)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 16)
  - CTC (Confederaciòn de Trabajadores de Cuba) (Folder 17)
  - Cambridge Opinion (Cuba issue) (Folder 18)
  - Canadian articles on Cuba (Folder 19)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 20)
  - Castro, Fidel (Box 3., Folder 21)
    - 1959-1960
    - 1961 (Folder 22)
      - March-April
      - May-June (Folder 23)
      - July-August (Folder 1)
      - September-October (Folder 2)
      - November-December (Folder 3)
      - December 2 (Folder 4)
    - 1962 (Folder 5)
      - January-May
      - June-September (Box 4., Folder 6)
      - October-December (Folder 7)
    - 1963 (Folder 8)
      - January-April
      - May (Folder 9)
      - June (Folder 10)
      - July (Folder 11)
      - August (Folder 12)
      - September-October (Folder 13)
      - November (Folder 14)
    - 1963
      - December (Box 5., Folder 15)
    - 1964
      - January-March (Folder 16)
      - April-August (Folder 17)
      - September-December (Folder 18)
    - 1965 (Folder 19)
    - 1966 (Folder 20)
  - Source material (Folder 21)
  - Castro, Juanita (Folder 1)
  - Castro, Raul (Folder 2)
    - 1959
    - 1961 (Box 6., Folder 3)
    - 1962 (Folder 4)
    - 1963 (Folder 5)
    - 1964-1965 (Folder 6)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 7)
  - Chile (Folder 8)
  - Cienfuegos (1957) (Folder 9)
  - Cienfuegos, Camilo (Folder 10)
  - Coexistence with Castro (Folder 11)
  - Confession trials in Cuba (Folder 12)
  - Congreso Pro-Unidad (1961) (Folder 13)
  - Corinthia (1957) (Folder 14)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 15)
  - Cuba, miscellaneous (Folder 16)
    - Pre-Castro period (1)
    - Pre-Castro period (2) (Folder 17)
    - 1959 (Folder 18)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 7., Folder 19)
    - 1962 (Folder 20)
    - 1963 (Folder 21)
    - 1964 (Folder 22)
    - 1965 (1) (Folder 23)
    - 1965 (2) (Folder 24)
    - 1966 (1) (Folder 25)
    - 1966 (2) (Folder 26)
  - The Cuban Report (Box 8., Folder 27)
  - Daniel, Jean (Folder 1)
  - Directorio (Folder 2)
  - Domestic problems (Post 1959) (Folder 3)
  - Dorticòs, Osvaldo (Folder 4)
    - 1960-1963
    - 1964-1965 (Folder 5)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 6)
  - Economía (Folder 7)
  - Economic (Folder 8)
    - 1963
    - 1964 (Folder 9)
    - Social (Folder 10)
  - Economics, miscellaneous (1) (Folder 11)
  - Economics, miscellaneous (2) (Folder 12)
  - Economics, miscellaneous (3) (Box 9., Folder 13)
  - Education (Folder 14)
  - Ejército Libertador (Folder 15)
  - Escalante, Aníbal (Folder 16)
  - Estudios sobre el Comunismo (Folder 17)
  - Exile leaders (Folder 18)
  - Exile organizations (1) (Folder 19)
  - Exile organizations (2) (Folder 20)
  - Exile publications (1) (Folder 21)
  - Exile publications (2) (Box 10., Folder 22)
  - Exile publications (3) (Folder 23)
  - Exiles, Fagen (Folder 24)
  - Exiles, miscellaneous (Folder 25)
  - FORDC (Frente Obrero Revolucionario Democrático de Cuba) (Folder 26)
  - Foreign realtions (Post- 1959) (Folder 27)
  - Free Cuba News (Folder 28)
  - French articles on Cuba (Folder 29)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 1)
  - Granma (Folder 2)
  - Guevara, Ernesto "Che" (Folder 3)
    - 1959-1961
    - 1962 (Box 11., Folder 4)
    - 1963 (Folder 5)
    - 1964 (Folder 6)
    - 1965 (Folder 7)
  - Originals of "Pasajes de la Guerra Revolutionaria" (Folder 8)
  - Guiteras, Antonio (Folder 9)
  - Halperin, Ernst (Folder 10)
  - Humanismo (Mexico) (Folder 11)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 12)
  - Information Bulletin (Folder 13)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 14)
  - Johnson, Paul and Kingsley Martin (Folder 15)
  - Labor conditions (Folder 16)
  - Latin American communism (Box 12., Folder 17)
  - Law (Folder 18)
  - Liborio (Folder 19)
  - Macaulay, Neil (Folder 20)
  - Mambisas (Folder 21)
  - Masò, Fausto (Folder 22)
  - Matthews, Herbert (Folder 23)
  - Maton, Húber (Folder 24)
  - Meneses, Enrique (Folder 25)
  - Mexico (1955-1956) (Folder 26)
  - Military (1) (Folder 27)
  - Military (2) (Folder 28)
  - Military (3) (Box 13., Folder 29)
  - Military, Barrera (Folder 30)
  - Military, miscellaneous (Folder 31)
  - Minor Cuban leaders (Folder 1)
  - Mirò Cardona, José (Folder 1a)
  - Missile crisis (Folder 2)
    - 1962 October-December
    - articles (Folder 3)
    - USSR, China, etc. (Box 14., Folder 4)
  - Moncada (Folder 5)
  - Monthly Review (Folder 6)
  - ORI (Organizaciones Revolucionarias Integradas) (Folder 7)
  - Ordoqui, Joaquín (Folder 8)
  - PURS (Partido Unido de la Revoluciòn Socialista) (Folder 9)
  - Pardo Llada, José (Folder 10)
  - Pasquín (Folder 11)
  - Patria (Folder 12)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 13)
  - Pazos, Felipe (Folder 14)
  - Political prisoners (Folder 15)
  - Popular (Folder 16)
  - Pre-Moncada period (Folder 16a)
  - Pre-Sierra period (Folder 16b)
  - Reloj (Folder 17)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 18)
  - Roa, Raul (Folder 19)
  - Roca, Blas (Folder 20)
  - Rodríguez, Carlos Rafael (Box 15., Folder 21)
    - 1962-1963
    - 1964-1965 (Folder 22)
  - Rodríguez, Marcos (trial) (Folder 23)
  - Sánchez Arango, Aureliano (Folder 24)
  - Sartre, Jean Paul (Folder 25)
  - Sierra Maestra (Folder 26)
  - Stevenson, Adlai (Folder 1)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 2)
  - Thomas, Hugh (Folder 3)
  - Transportation (Folder 4)
  - Tretiak, Daniel (Folder 5)
  - Tricontinental conference, 1966 (Box 16., Folder 6)
  - Trimestre Econòmico (Folder 7)
  - Trotskyists (Folder 8)
  - Twenty-sixth of July Movement (Folder 9)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 10)
  - L'Unita (Folder 11)
  - United States aid to Cuba (Folder 12)
  - United States articles on Cuba (Folder 13)
    - 1960-1961
    - 1962 (Folder 14)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 17., Folder 15)
  - United States policy (1) (Folder 16)
  - United States policy (2) (Folder 17)
  - United States policy (3) (Folder 18)
  - United States policy (4) (Folder 19)
  - United States students in Cuba (Folder 20)
  - Women in Cuba (Folder 21)
  - Aragòn, Ernesto de (Box 23., Folder 1)
  - correspondence
  - Carillo, Justo (Folder 2)
    - (1) correspondence, manuscript
    - (2) correspondence, documents (Folder 2a)
    - (3) manuscript (Folder 2b)
  - Chibás, Raul (Folder 2c)
  - manuscript
  - Draper, Theodore (Folder 3)
    - (1) manuscript and notes
    - (2) manuscript (Folder 3a)
    - (3) manuscript - copy 1 (Box 24., Folder 3b)
    - (4) manuscript - copy 2 (Folder 3c)
  - Godoy, Joaquín (Folder 4)
    - correspondence
  - Llerena, Mario (Folder 4a)
    - manuscript
  - Martínez Araras, Raul (Folder 4b)
    - memos
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 25., Folder 7)
  - Pazos, Felipe (Folder 8)
    - correspondence, manuscript
  - Sánchez Arango, Aureliano (Folder 9)
    - correspondence
  - Simòn, Luis (Folder 9a)
    - correspondence, manuscript
  - State Department (Folder 10)
    - correspondence
  - Suárez, Andrés (Folder 11)
    - manuscript
  - Twenty-sixth of July Movement in Exile (Folder 11a)
  - Unidentified correspondence (Folder 11b)
  - Volsky, George (Box 26., Folder 12)
    - reports
      - 1963 June-December
      - 1964 January-June (Folder 13)
      - 1964 July-December (Folder 14)
      - 1965 January-December (Folder 15)
      - 1966 January-December (Folder 16)
    - manuscripts (Folder 17)
- Dominican Republic. Inventory of the collection of material on the Dominican Republic crises with emphasis on United State involvement, 1963-1966
  - Argentina (Box 18., Folder 1)
  - Background (Folder 2)
  - Balaguer, Joaquín (Folder 3)
  - Bosch, Juan (1) (Folder 4)
  - Bosch, Juan (2) (Folder 4a)
  - CIA (Central Intelligence Agency) (Folder 5)
  - Catholic Church (Folder 5a)
  - Clippings (Folder 6)
    - 1965 April 25-May 9
    - 1965 May 10-30 (Folder 7)
    - 1965 June-July (Folder 8)
    - 1965 August-December (Folder 9)
    - 1966 January-February (Box 19., Folder 10)
    - 1966 March-June (Folder 11)
  - Clippings, Spanish language (Folder 12)
    - 1965
    - 1966 (Folder 12a)
  - Committee for Free Elections (Folder 13)
  - Communist role in DR (Folder 14)
  - Congressional Record (Folder 15)
  - Dominican-Cuba (1965-1966) (Folder 16)
  - Dominican leaders (Folder 16a)
  - Dominican students (Folder 17)
  - Economic and social conditions (Box 20., Folder 18)
  - Withdrawn (Folder 19)
  - Election, 1966 (Folder 20)
  - Frente de Organizaciones Democráticas Constitucionalistas (FODECO) (Folder 20a)
  - Fulbright, J. William (Folder 21)
  - Imbert, Antonio (Folder 22)
  - Kennedy, Robert (Folder 23)
  - Labor role in the DR (Folder 24)
  - Latin America Report (Free Cuba News) (Folder 25)
  - Listin Diario, 1965 April 26 (Folder 26)
  - Movimiento Popular Dominicano (MPD) (Folder 27)
  - Movimiento Revolucionario "14 de Junio" (1J4) (Folder 28)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1965 (Folder 1)
  - New York World Telegram, 1965 (Folder 2)
  - 1963 coup (1) (Folder 3)
  - 1963 coup (2) (Folder 4)
  - OAS (1) (Box 21., Folder 5)
  - OAS (2) (Folder 6)
  - OAS (3) (Folder 7)
  - PRD-PRSC pact (Folder 8)
  - Partido Revolucionario Social Cristiano (PRSC) (Folder 8a)
  - Partido Socialista Popular (PSP) and Partido Comunista Dominicano (PDC) (Folder 8b)
  - Police and military (Folder 8c)
  - The Reporter, 1965-66 (Folder 9)
  - Right-wing material, 1965-66 (Folder 10)
  - Source material (Folder 11)
  - Trujillo, Rafael (Box 22., Folder 12)
  - Trujillo, Ramfis (Folder 12a)
  - United Nations (Folder 13)
  - United States officials (Folder 14)
  - United States policy (1) (Folder 15)
  - United States policy (2) (Folder 16)
  - United States Senate hearings on DR (Folder 16a)
  - Ventura memoirs (Folder 17)
  - Bosch, Juan (Box 27., Folder 1)
  - Catholics (Folder 1a)
  - Draper, Theodore (1) (Folder 2)
  - Draper, Theodore (2) (Folder 2a)
  - Espinal, Emmanuel (Folder 2b)
  - Fernández Domínguez, Rafael (Folder 2c)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Folder 4)
  - United States Senate hearings on the DR (Folder 5)
  - Volman, Sacha (Folder 6)
- Communist Party. Inventory of the collection of material pertaining mostly to the Communist Party in America (some socialist material included), 1912-1958
  - Russian propaganda. Hearing before a subcommittee of the committee on foreign relations United States Senate, 1920 (Box 28.)
  - Minutes, National Committee - T.U.E.L., 1925-1929. Photocopies
  - Session of American Commission on 1924 May 6. Darcy
  - Workers Party of America. Minutes of first convention 1921 December. Mimeograph
  - Zimmerman material. Zack letter 1927 July 29 to ECCI. Photostat
  - Wicks material. Articles from the Proletarian, 1921-22
  - Thesis on the Present Economic and Political Situation and the Policy of the Workers Party submitted by John Pepper and C. E. Ruthenberg, 1923 November thesis (Wicks material, original, mimeograph)
  - Thesis on Our Labor Party Policy, 1923 August 24 (Wicks material, original, mimeograph)
  - Correspondence to W. J. Ghent, Philip Klarnet, etc.
  - Minutes. Political Committee, 1926-27, numerous photostats
  - Miscellaneous printed, photostated material pertaining to communism
  - Odd sheets; index of TUC minutes, 1925-1928. Louis Nemzer, Coolidge regarding La Follette, etc. (Box 29.)
  - Minutes. Political Committee, 1928 January-June. Photocopies, including Secretariat 1928 January 16
  - Minutes. Organization Conference, 1928 May 28. Photocopy
  - Minutes. Resolution on Trade Union Work (by Foster), 1928 May 30. Photocopy
  - Wicks' letter to Engdahl, 1929 May 9. Report by Lovestone Delegation in Moscow. Original
  - Minutes. Trade Union Committee - C.E.C., 1925-26. Photocopies
  - Minutes. National Committee - T.U.E.L., 1923-28. Originals
  - Minutes. Workers Party, 1923-24
  - Minutes. Extracts from Minutes 1923, 1924 copies
  - Minutes. Executive council, 1924 May 14
  - TU Minutes. Duplicates, photocopies
  - Cannon (Box 30.)
  - Swabeck, Arne
  - Correspondence
  - Notes, 1919-1929
  - American Communism material
  - The Labor Herald, 1923 November
  - American Communism miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous letters to Draper?
  - Minutes. Political Committee, 1928 November. Call to Sixth Convention 1928 November 28
  - Traditional Right Wing in the American Party and Our Fight Against It
  - Wicks
  - Wolfe, Bertram D.
  - 1922 Minutes (purchased from Leon Kramer)
  - Katterfeld, L. E. Taped interview by Theodore Draper, 1956 September 8. Typed
  - Meeting of executive bureau (RILU), 1928 January 3. Report of Comrade Browder on American question (Trade Union). Photocopy
  - Minutes. Left Wing Section, 1919. Photostats
  - Bedacht, Max
  - Correspondence with Ted Draper, 1954 December-1955 January. Originals and typed duplicates
  - Socialist documents, 1919-1921
  - Socialist Party Collection, Duke University
  - Wicks' statement to the Comintern "Observations on the factional situation in the American Party," Moscow, 1929 April 15. Original
  - "History of the Communist Movement in America" by Alexander Bittelman, 1923-24. (Special Comm. to investigate Comm. activities, 1930). Photocopy
  - Negro. Cyril V. Briggs (Box 31.)
  - Cannon, J. P.
  - Cannon-Draper correspondence put on film 1958 July
  - Eastman, Max
  - Negro. Otto Hall and Harry Haywood
  - Kahanovitch, L. M. Organizational structure of the Russian Communist Party, probably 1925. Mimeograph
  - Kruse, William
  - Ruthenberg to Comintern. Letter dated 1924 April 11 (Browder material)
  - Sandburg, Carl. Correspondence with T.D. and photostat of C.S. statement in Stockholm, correspondence dated 1956 February 25
  - Sandburg, Carl
  - Spector, Maurice. Interview 1957 November 25
  - Schachtman, Max. Interview T.D., 1954 May 25
  - Weisbord, Albert
  - Wicks' speech on Comintern Moscow, 1929 April 21. Lovestone delegation at American Commission (Wicks material, original)
  - Minutes. Political Committee Secretariat, 1927 November-December. Photocopies (Box 32.)
  - Minutes. Secretariat, Political Committee, 1927 October. Photocopies
  - Minutes. Central Executive Committee, Secretariat Political Committee, 1927 September. Photocopies, index to minutes, 1927 September-December
  - Wicks material, lectures on China, 1927
  - Lovestone's letter to the comintern on behalf of Pepper, 1924. (Browder material, copied by Browder from original)
  - Appeal to comintern on behalf of Pepper by Robert Minor, 1924. (Wicks material, original)
  - T.U.U.L.-T.U.E.L., 1922-1930. Contents of file of documents dealing with T.U.U.L.-T.U.E.L.
  - Minutes. Political Committee, 1927 January-August. Photocopies
  - Minutes. Trade Union Committee - C.E.C., 1927. Photocopies
  - Minutes, 1922. Photocopies (purchased from Leon Kramer)
  - Minutes. Gitlow exhibits (typed) copies. Executive Council, Secretariat, Politbureau, Political committee, etc., 1924, 1924, 1926
  - May Day of Revolution (leaflet) United Communist Party of America, 1920? (Wicks material, original)
  - Minutes. Central Executive Committee Communist Party of America, 1919 November 15-17, 18 (Wicks material, original, mimeograph)
  - Minutes. Central Executive Committee Communist Party of America, 1919 November 15-18. Photocopies
  - Theodore Draper's notes and research covering the years ca. 1912-1953 in preparation for his writing about communism and the Communist Party in America (Box 33-34.)
  - Newspaper clippings and excerpts from Communist Party literature ca. 1923-1929. Copies. 4 notebooks (Box 35.)
  - 12 pamphlets mostly issued by United States Communist Party, 1896-1956 (Box 36.)
  - Final manuscript of American Communism and Soviet Russia, by Theodore Draper (Box 37.)